<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Inferring extirpation in potential habitat on IMERSS</title>
    <link>/docs/extirpation_potential/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Inferring extirpation in potential habitat on IMERSS</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <atom:link href="/docs/extirpation_potential/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Inverse distance prior</title>
      <link>/docs/extirpation_potential/distance_prior/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/docs/extirpation_potential/distance_prior/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Estimating the likelihood of a plant’s occurrence beyond the extent of its historical habitat presents a Wallacean dilemma, as species often exhibit restricted distributions despite the apparent availability of suitable habitat (Lomolino, Riddle and Brown., 2006). To address this dilemma, we applied the negative exponential distance weighting system widely used in metapopulation ecology to model patch-occupancy dynamics (Hanski, 1994; Hanski et al., 2017; Yeiser et al., 2021; Hanski &amp; Ovaskainen, 2002). This method was chosen for its analytical simplicity, based on the assumption that patch occupancy probabilities decrease with varying distance from historical source populations, depending on the rarity patterns of target plants.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rarity types</title>
      <link>/docs/extirpation_potential/rarity_types/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/docs/extirpation_potential/rarity_types/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;xxxx&#34;&gt;XXXX&lt;a class=&#34;td-heading-self-link&#34; href=&#34;#xxxx&#34; aria-label=&#34;Heading self-link&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Calibrating&#xA;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kernel validation</title>
      <link>/docs/extirpation_potential/kernel_validation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/docs/extirpation_potential/kernel_validation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For detected species, negative-exponential kernels were estimated empirically by regressing the distances of species detections from the position of initial records, against the background of unsuccessful detections. This was done with the brms package (Bürkner, 2017) using Markov Chain Monte Carlo sampling in STAN. Our regression applies the Bernoulli distribution family to the target detection via a modelling function&#xA;\(occupancy_i 〜 q .exp( d_i) \) where  is the kernel width, q scales the overall detection rate (not of interest to this analysis) and di is the distance from historical habitat of occupancy observation \(occupancy_i\).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Example</title>
      <link>/docs/extirpation_potential/example/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/docs/extirpation_potential/example/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Before the beginning of the BioGaliano project in 2015, a total of 607 vascular plant species were reported for Galiano Island, represented by 1,698 records, including 446 herbarium specimens (Fig. 1).&#xA;After five years of concerted search effort, amounting to &amp;gt;18,000 observations, we documented 560 species on the project, confirming 433/607 historical species reports (71% of the historically reported diversity) and adding 127 new species to the list.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
